Daf is דף ע"ו daf ayin vav and we start at the
bottom of ע"ה עמוד ב' ayin hey amud bet at the משנה.
mishna. Okay, so we had a כלל גדול klal gadol about the
ל"ט מלאכות lamed tet melachos and the גמרא gemara has made dealt
with that very quickly compared to the rest of the מסכת, masechet,
but we will be
seeing obviously the rest of the מסכת masechet will be to some
degree an elaboration on these categories, although not always exactly clear which
way how they are fitting in and which aspects they are elaborating
on, but we will see much more of the מלאכות melachos as
we continue. We now turn to another כלל גדול. klal gadol. So
the משנה mishna at the bottom here, or כלל, klal, of ע"ה
עמוד ב', ayin hey amud bet, ועוד כלל אחר אמרו, ve-od klal
acher amru, they said another כלל: klal: כל הכשר להצניע ומצניעין כמוהו
והוציאו בשבת חייב. kol ha-kasher le-hatznia matznin kamohu ve-hotzio be-shabbos chayav. So
quite surprisingly you're expecting a כלל, klal, you're expecting something that applies
to say you know the totality of שבת, shabbos, and all of
a sudden we are we are pulled right back into the world
of carrying, of הוצאה. hotza'ah. We have like three chapters of it
you know and it started off at the very beginning of the
מסכת masechet and now immediately we are pulled back into it and
that's also going to be the whole next chapter. So again it
certainly is worth mentioning, recognizing the centrality of הוצאה hotza'ah to the
discussions of שבת shabbos and there's actually a whole מסכת masechet that
comes next, עירובין, eruvin, that's to some degree is devoted to that.
So the next כלל klal is not about all of שבת, shabbos,
it's about carrying. And what is that כלל? klal? Anything that is
a fit to be secreted, to be put aside, and you put
aside something like that meaning it is a type of an object
that normally is treated as of value. The גמרא gemara will say
what does that exclude? But a type of an object that you
know is not like everybody discards, it's some type of an object
that is kept and not discarded and that that amount of it
is normally the amount put aside. Sometimes you can have an object
of value you know but if it's a tiny bit you would
throw it out. So א' aleph it has to be a type
of an object that is of value and ב' bet it has
to be a minimum amount that is normally set aside.
חייב חטאת עליו, chayav chatas alav, if you bring that out on
שבת shabbos you are חייב חטאת. chayav chatas. So basically we are
talking about the minimum size for הוצאה, hotza'ah, the minimum size for
carrying. And now we're talking about it in an abstract sense before
we get down to the particulars and the abstract criteria for carrying
is it has to be a type of thing that is normally
kept and not discarded and a minimum amount that is normally kept.
וכל שאינו כשר להצניע ואין מצניעין כמוהו, ve-kol she-eino kasher le-hatznia ve-ein
matznin kamohu,
anything that is either not normally kept or that amount of it
is not normally kept והוציאו בשבת ve-hotzio be-shabbos אינו חייב, eino chayav,
you don't transgress אלא המצניעו, ela ha-matznio, but somebody could transgress. If
you happen subjectively to put it aside then you for you you're
חייב. chayav. Okay? So normally what you have here is I don't
know a half a piece of gum. So most people would throw
out a half a piece of gum or maybe we can talk
about pre-chewed gum, okay. Most people would throw out pre-chewed gum but
you are planning on getting back to it later okay and you've
put it aside, you put in your little wrapper you're gonna get
back to it later. So everybody else would be exempt but for
you you're חייב chayav because for you it is something of value.
So this is quite surprising because almost always we expect that the
שיעור, shiur, a minimum amount, is an objective amount and end of
story and there's no question about your subjective issue. Sometimes we might
want to talk about a class of people, we talk about like
עשירים ashirim versus עניים, aniyim, size of a garment that you know
rich people throw away but poor people will still use as a
patch. But again what is quite surprising here is that we go
on the individual level that if for you it's valuable that you're
חייב. chayav. And again what is also fascinating is every one of
the ל"ט מלאכות lamed tet melachos we have to know what is
the minimum amount. Some of it was already mentioned in the previous
משנה mishna and גמרא, gemara, but for some reason again we are
honing in on הוצאה hotza'ah and we are now going to spend
an enormous amount of time the remaining משניות mishnayos here in the
next פרק perek talking about minimum sizes specifically for carrying.
Yes, it just seems to be a very strange terminology להצניע. le-hatznia.
To me that sounds like something you're gonna keep for a while
as opposed to you know...
Yeah, I think it basically means as I said that you're not
going to throw it
out, okay, but yeah anytime soon, right, yeah I can't say more
about that.
Yeah, can you make a distinction between
that it's important or value to you and the minimum amount?
Yeah, because there are some type of objects that everybody throws out,
okay, so we don't even have to talk about them about minimum
amounts, okay. So the גמרא gemara is going to ask what are
those objects alright.
If I took out the garbage it's not a problem because no
one wants them, no...
well, I don't know because there are things in it that you
could feed to animals and so on. Let's take a look at
the גמרא. gemara. But what I meant to ask
is we're saying it's subjective about this is important to somebody so
that's חייב chayav for, but is there also the qualification of minimum
amount of that thing that...
Oh yes yes when it says at the end, I see, it
says אלא המצניעו ela ha-matznio means that if
you set
aside... the minimum amount. Yes. So your subjective reality would dictate. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. כל הכשר להצניע לאפוקי מאי?
Kol hakasher lehatznia lafukei mai?
So anything that it as a type of thing that is normally
sort of set aside protected, not thrown out. What is that coming
to exclude? What types of things might everybody just obviously discard? So
רב פפא אמר, Rav Pappa amar, לאפוקי דם נדה, lafukei dam nida,
to exclude a woman's menstrual
blood. That is obviously something that of course would go like Michael
said, you know, things that obviously you would throw out, but nobody
has any use for the menstrual blood. All right, we're not talking
about that. We're not talking that it's a little bit and on
some cloth that she needs to show to somebody, we're just talking
about she's in the middle of her menstrual cycle and there's a
lot of bleeding. So obviously the soiled pad is thrown out and
nobody has any reason for keeping that.
Oh, that could be an interesting example too. I know, so that's
what I said, I knew you, I knew, right. Why did they
specifically, why didn't they pick a rock that was used for wiping
yourself, what they had instead of toilet paper? Although maybe sometimes they
reuse the rock after it dries, but I'm serious, I'm not making
it up. Anyway, but right, it is very funny that that's the
thing they hone in on is, you know, women's menstrual blood. Let's
just see the other answer. מר עוקבא אמר, Mar Ukva amar, לאפוקי
עצי אשרה, lafukei atzei ashera, to exclude אשרה ashera wood which is
wood that has to ritually be, you know, is forbidden in benefit
and has to be burnt and destroyed. So obviously you have no
use for it. So מאן דאמר, man de'amar, דם נדה, dam nida,
if you say menstrual blood, כל שכן עצי אשרה, kol shekein atzei
ashera, certainly אשרה ashera
which is not only socially or, you know, you don't have any
use for, but הלכה-ly halakha you have to destroy. But מאן דאמר,
man de'amar, עצי אשרה, atzei ashera, but if you say אשרה ashera
wood, that is something that הלכה-ly halakha you can't do anything with.
אבל דם נדה, Aval dam nida, but menstrual blood, מצניע ליה לשונרא,
matznia lei lashunra,
you can put it aside because maybe your cat will want to
eat it up.
So again, very disturbing the way the גמרא Gemara is sort of
dealing with that. ואידך, Ve'idakh,
and what would the other one say back? No, כיון דחלשה לא
מצניע ליה. kivan dechalsha lo matznia lei. Since it makes you sick,
you won't put it aside. Now you could have said the cat
will become sick, but רש"י Rashi actually says that there was somehow
a belief that if you fed it, this to a cat, you
would become sick. And yeah, if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י
Rashi
says: כיון דחלשה, kivan dechalsha, second wide line, המאכיל דם אדם לחתול
נעשה חלש אותו אדם. hamakhil dam adam lechatul na'aseh chalash oto adam.
Any דם. dam. But right, but one wonders if there's also maybe
a specific issue associated with this נדה, nida, which I blood which,
you know, we know beyond the הלכות halakhot of נדה, nida, outside
of the גמרא, Gemara, we have evidence of the idea of a
lot of taboos that were associated with it. But again, רש"י Rashi
here is broadening it to any דם האדם. dam ha'adam.
So those are the two opinions about the types of things. Now
תוספות Tosafot points out that in other גמרות, Gemaras, it actually says
that עצי אשרה, atzei ashera, דוקא davka is something that you do
set aside because you have to do the מצוה mitzvah of burning
it. So therefore, even though you have no use for it in
terms of benefit, it is something that you want to hold onto
and because you have to take it and burn it and do
something with it. So again it's interesting this גמרא Gemara puts it
in the category of something that obviously you have no use for.
Ari you had a question?
Do we need a הוה אמינא hava amina before a couple chapters
ago that you couldn't, you couldn't have a pad because it was
to protect your clothing, but here we're saying that it's okay because
it's worthless.
No, one was a question that the, oh I see what you're
saying, you're saying if the pad already got... that's a good question.
Why do we say you couldn't wear a pad, why was that
carrying if so, the, it could be it's a difference before it
got bloodstained and after it got bloodstained, right? After it got totally
bloodstained and it no longer has any value, although if it's still
there and still absorbing blood, then while it's still there it might
still have the value of being able to absorb blood. So it
might be the question about and the מצניע, matznia, it might be
the question about at which stage you're at, right? But once it's
ready to be discarded, you can no longer... but that's a good
point. So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא, Amar
Rabbi Yose bar Chanina, היא דלא כרבי שמעון. hi d'lo k'Rabbi Shimon.
This משנה mishna is not like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Why? דאי
כרבי שמעון, De'ei k'Rabbi Shimon, because according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
we're going to read in a next, in a coming up משנה,
mishna, הא אמר, ha amar, he says: לא אמרו כל השיעורין הללו
אלא למצניהן. Lo amru kol hashi'urin halalau ela lematzniyeihen.
All the minimum שיעורים shi'urim that we're about to give in all
the following משניות mishnayot are not said for your standard person. They
are said for the type of person that normally sets these things
aside. You could even read it as normally sets them aside or
you could read only set for a person who actually did set
it aside. But for a type of person who either did not
set it aside, or for a type of person who normally this
is something not of a value even if they're a value for
most people, for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that's not enough. So רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says this idea of a minimum שיעור shi'ur that
we're about to list in the coming משנה mishna is not a
universal. This משנה mishna says here are the minimum שיעורים shi'urim that
apply to everyone. If you are the type of person that sets
smaller... things aside or more discarded things aside, then you'll be חייב
chayav even earlier. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, these minimum שיעורים
shiurim don't apply to everyone. They only apply to people to whom
they're relevant. They only apply to the class of people for whom
this is meaningful, or to people who specifically set it aside. But
if you're a type of a person who does, who this is
not meaningful and or you didn't specifically set aside, two reeds, of
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, then for you only a larger amount you'd
be חייב. chayav. Okay, so our משנה Mishnah is not that way,
because our משנה Mishnah says everybody is חייב chayav for the following
amounts and some people are חייב chayav for even less. One minute,
וכל שאינו כשר להצניע, v'chol she'eino kashar l'hatznia, now we look at
the second part of the משנה, Mishnah, that if something is less
than these minimum amounts, then, then the only person חייב chayav is
the one who actually did set it aside, and again that's quite
fascinating that we could have subjective שיעורים, shiurim, something we normally do
not have. So אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, הא דלא כרבי
שמעון בן אלעזר. ha d'lo k'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. This is not
like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, this is not
like another opinion. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught a principle, this is not
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, סתם רבי שמעון stam Rabbi Shimon is רבי
שמעון בר יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. We taught in a ברייתא,
baraita, כלל אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, clal amar Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar, כל שאינו כשר להצניע ואין מצניעין כמותו, col she'eino kashar l'hatznia
v'ein matzninim k'moto, anything that normally is not of a type of
object that's normally set aside, or this minimum amount is not normally
set aside, this amount is not normally set aside, והוכשר לזה, v'huchshar
l'zeh, and for this person oh this is something that's worthwhile, והצניעו,
v'hitznio, and he set it aside, ובא אחר והוציאו, u'ba acher v'hotzio,
and now somebody else came and took it out. So my half-piece
of chewed gum that I put aside for later use, now Michael
came and took it out. So you know what? נתחייב זה במחשבה
של זה. nitchayev zeh b'machshava shel zeh. Michael is now חייב chayav
because I gave it subjective significance. Okay, so once I made it
significant and I'm the owner of it, presumably I'm in a position
to give it significance, then I have defined it as significant for
the rest of the world. So on the one hand that seems
of course very like unfair. Just because you made it important why
should I be dictated? But I have to tell you that part
of the partly I am somewhat attracted to this because I'm very
disturbed by the idea that the sizes are different for every person.
That you know for me I set this aside that's my size,
for you you set something else aside meaning if you don't do
anything special they're the same but every person can create their own
minimum size. So at least according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, at
least once you've created a minimum size then it affects other people
as well. So it's not completely just for you. So anyway that
is an interesting position that is not what the משנה Mishnah says.
The משנה Mishnah says if you set it aside it'll be different
for you. Yes.
I want to get back to
like garbage. Most people aren't really like concerned garbage, so what does
it mean just because like some...
Okay, so we will see that, I understood your question, we will
see that in the משנה, Mishnah, and the משנה Mishnah actually says
that no, that even if for you it is not important, if
objectively this is something of value and look look for people search
through garbage I mean sadly animals go to garbage I mean people
could use that type of stuff to feed. So let's take a
look at the משנה Mishnah because we were actually...
Even though, even if you throw away something not knowing it's valuable
to someone...
Yeah, then you'd be a שוגג. shogeg. Oh not only it's valuable
to someone else but again there is going to be minimum objective
sizes. That's the important thing. Your subjective importance can make things smaller
things important. But when we define minimum that applies even if it's
even if for you it is insignificant. That's the whole point. That
for you minimum is since objectively this is something that is of
value therefore even
therefore regardless of what you think about it you're חייב. chayav. If
you weren't aware you'd be a שוגג. shogeg.
Even if no poor people near here that is going to get
this right...
Right, presumably, right. So let's take a look at the next משנה.
Mishnah. I mean the question is what part of society do you
look at? 51%? A non-trivial segment? How exactly do you determine is
not clear. Let's take a look at the next part of the
משנה Mishnah at the next משנה. Mishnah.
המוציא תבן כמלא פי פרה, hamotzi teven k'mlo pi para, if somebody
takes out straw that would fit in the mouth of a cow
because straw is what you feed cows. The cow mouth is pretty
big, but other smaller animals don't want straw. So the minimum amount
of straw is the amount that fits in the in the mouth
of a cow.
עצה כמלא פי גמל, atza k'mlo pi gamal, or עצה atza which
is some type of like a straw of legumes, I don't know
exactly the reality but that's what the גמרא Gemara describes it, then
that is something that cows don't eat and the only animal that
eats that is camels. Camels have a much larger mouth. Okay, but
it's a so therefore the minimum size is bigger because no animal
smaller than a camel eats this food and therefore the minimum use
of this food is to feed a camel and the camel's mouth
presumably you'd be like the significant minimum amount is the amount I'm
you know is the amount to actually less than this is not
enough is not significant. It's only significant if it can actually be
a whole bite, a whole a whole feed for for camel.
A whole camel or what?
All right, I don't know. עמיר amir it's a good question. עמיר
כמלא פי טלה, amir k'mlo pi taleh, if it is some type
of like grain husks, not grain husks...
עמיר, amir, you say
straw? No not not
straw
they say for עמיר... amir... עמיר? amir? תבן teven is straw. You
say עמיר amir or... What does... I don't think so. רש״י Rashi
says it's...
what? קשדן. kashdan. קשדן. kashdan.
Really, that's the difference? Okay.
He says the first is for the stalks.
Yes, that's what I thought straw was. And what's the second? The
husks, right? Or something like that.
What does this refer for the sheep?
Well, עמיר Amir כמלא פי טלה, kemalo pi taleh, and it is
for the sheep.
All right, anyway. So anyway, I thought עמיר Amir was something was...
Rashi says קש, Kash, but I thought קש Kash was something different
than straw. I thought קש Kash was more like the I don't
know.
So anyway, עמיר, Amir, some other type of straw, but but more
edible than the straw that's fed to the cows, is כמלא פי
טלה, kemalo pi taleh, the amount that fits in the mouth of
a sheep. Because because a because a sheep is a smaller mouth,
but he won't eat the straw that you feed a cow, but
he'll eat this type of straw and therefore it's even that is
the minimum size. עשבים, Asavim, grass, which which again won't be eaten
by a sheep,
כמלא פי גדי, kemalo pi gedi, is by a goat. A goat
has a even a smaller mouth than a sheep and therefore grass
goes by or maybe it is eaten by a sheep, but it
doesn't matter because it's already eaten by something smaller. So you know
even if so right or even if for example this עמיר Amir
is eaten by a cow, I might have misstated it. If it's
eaten by something bigger it doesn't matter, you go by the smallest
thing that eats it. So the smallest thing that eats the עמיר,
Amir, is this this type of a straw is this sheep, but
a goat won't eat it. But now you have grass, grass is
eaten by sheep, right, you graze sheep, but it's also eaten by
goats. And therefore the grass goes by the amount that sits in
the mouth of a goat.
Now עלי שום ועלי בצלים, alei shum va'alei betzalim, if you have
leaves of garlic or leaves of onion, לחים כגרוגרת, lachim kegrogeret, if
they are moist and therefore edible by people. I don't know anybody
who normally eats onion leaves and garlic leaves, but maybe in the
time of the גמרא, Gemara, then it is like the size of
a of a pressed fig. Now the basic rule here is all
human food is the size of a pressed fig. Okay, that is
for whatever reason that's understood, although normally we define כזית kezayit is
the minimum amount to define an act of eating and a and
a pressed fig is larger than a כזית. kezayit. But if it
doesn't, presumably, fill you up to even a tiny degree, it is
not considered significant, so we go by the size of a pressed
fig a little bit more for significance once it's in the category
of human food. An interesting question would be, let's say it's both
human food and animal food and the animal food amount is smaller,
right? So would that animal category even lower the size? But the
general rule is once it's human food it is a pressed fig.
יבשים, Yeveshim, if these are dried leaves, so therefore no longer a
human food, כמלא פי גדי, kemalo pi gedi, it goes back to
what a goat would eat. Now, so again the basic rule is
you take the object, you look at the smallest, if it's a
food, the smallest thing that would eat it or the smallest mouth
of you know of those animals that eat it and that goes
by that size. So if this thing would be eaten by something
bigger it doesn't matter, but if it would be eaten by something
smaller like grass, it's eaten by a sheep but it's also eaten
by a goat, you go by the smaller you go by the
goat. What did you ask me then? Yeah, here we're talking about...
you can't like categorize animals.
That's a good question. You're right. Maybe since animals that are not
normally, right, that's a good point, animals that are not normally domestic
are not are I don't say I don't care about feeding those
other animals. So therefore we don't care, right, exactly. Thank you, that's
an excellent point. It's the animals you care about feeding because that
gives it significance to you. You're not talking about the fact that
the animals give it significance. It gives it significance to you because
you are concerned about the feeding of those types of animals. And
going back to you know Michael's issue about the garbage, it doesn't
matter if you own these animals or not. Right? So again we
go by the fact and doesn't you don't need fifty-five percent of
society to own these animals. The fact that there is it does
have objective value you know within society to feed these animals. Yes.
Are we assuming he was trying to skirt the issue of שבת?
Shabbos? Or is he just... No.
Yeah look some people might be trying to do it with less
than the minimum amount which is at least rabbinically if not biblically
forbidden, but we're not right now asking what the person's motivations are.
We're just saying has you actually transgressed, are you חייב חטאת chayav
chatas if you did it בשוגג? beshogeg? Why you would want to
do this, are you aware of what you're doing, that's a separate
question. Okay, let's let's finish let's read the end of the
משנה. Mishnah.
Okay, now ואין מצטרפין זה עם זה מפני שלא שוו בשיעוריהם. ve'ein
mitztarpin ze im ze mipnei shelo shavu bishureihem. They don't combine one
with another. If you have this let's say the amount of straw
that would go for a cow, but you have only three quarters
of the amount of the mouth of a cow of straw and
you add to it some of this you know עמיר Amir that
you feed a sheep with, then you can't combine them to say,
oh now those two together you know have a minimum size because
fundamentally those are go by different minimum amounts and you can't combine
things that are in categories of different amounts. We'll see about this
in... That's the real amount. And now again, I don't know why
three flakes? Is that all you feed your fish? Three flakes?
I mean I'm just saying because I know it's very little.
What? Okay, it could be very little. But again notice, just because
now for me, I'm not going to throw out half a mouthful
of straw because I'll wait till I get another half a mouthful
and feed my cow. So it's not the minimum amount that you
know, yes I will... this has some use for me, but right
now it's not enough to fully serve a particular use. Okay? So
I'm not going to go take this and feed my cow a
half of a mouthful, even though I'm going to save this half
a mouthful till I get more. So if your question about the
fish food, I don't care how small it is, but is this
the minimum amount that you would use before going over to your
aquarium? And if the answer is no, and you actually go over
to your aquarium you have a little bit more, then it's the
amount that you would go before you start dropping flakes in your
aquarium.
The other thing is they're usually in a container. You have to
take... is the container...
That we'll see about whether when they're in a container does the
container come בטל batel to the food. Okay, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי אצה, Mai atza, what is this אצה
atza that you feed that camels eat but cows don't eat, and
therefore you go by a camel? אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda,
תבן שבמיני קטניות. teven she-minei kitniyot. קטניות, kitniyot, it is some type
of a straw of some type of a legume. Okay, so again
I don't know, it doesn't even tell you what type of a
legume. כי אתא רב דימי אמר, Ki ata Rav Dimi amar, המוציא
תבן כמלוא פי פרה לגמל. hamotzi teven kemolei pi para legamal. Now
we get into interesting question about the subjective reality. You have decided
you are going to feed straw to your camel. Okay, your camel,
because your camel also eats straw. Meaning, your cow doesn't eat this
אצה, atza, but the straw that you feed your cow will also
be eaten by a camel. So if you are taking it out
specifically to feed your camel, maybe for you this is not yet
a minimum amount, maybe subjectively the minimum can go up, not just
down. So what's the הלכה? halakha? רבי יוחנן אמר חייב. Rabbi Yochanan
amar chayav. You're חייב chayav because it's still the minimum amount for
cows. ריש לקיש אמר פטור, Reish Lakish amar patur, you're exempt because
for you this has no yet no longer has any significance. Maybe
that becomes like Michal's case about the garbage. So for you it's
not yet significant, then you are off the hook. That's pretty shocking
that we're being lenient based on your subjective reality. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: באורתא אמר רבי יוחנן הכי. Be-ursa amar Rabbi
Yochanan hachi. At night, that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said. He
said you're חייב chayav even if you want it for your camel
and it's not yet a significant enough amount.
אמצפרא, A-mztfara, you know, sometimes when you look at things in the
morning they look different. So in the morning, הדר ביה, hadar bei,
he reversed himself. He said, 'Ah! טאקע ריש לקיש!' Taka Reish Lakish!
Now it's wild, both רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish say that based on your subjective reality, you could actually get
off the hook because for you this is not yet enough. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, שפיר עביד
דהדר. shapir avid de-hadar. It's good that he was right to reverse
himself. דלא חזי לגמל, De-lo chazi legamal, it's not fit for the
camel. Now we have three opinions. Now there's a unanimity that if
for you you want it for your camel and this is not
what it's significant for yet, you're off the hook. Again, doesn't mean
it's מותר, muttar, but you're not- you haven't transgressed. אמר ליה אביי,
Amar leh Abaye, now אביי Abaye reverses this whole trend. אדרבה! Adderaba!
What are you talking about? The opposite! קמייתא שפירא. Kimei kahrna ishtafar.
What he said first, what he said before you know at the
night made sense. דחזי לפרה. De-hachazi le-para. There's an objective reality that
this amount is fit for a cow. And since for other people
this is a significant minimum amount, how does your subjective desire to
feed it to a camel get you off the hook? אלא כי
אתא רבין אמר, Ela ki ata Ravin amar, when רבין Ravin came
from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, and normally רבין Ravin says things in
the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, but here it doesn't say
explicitly in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אמר, amar, he
said it very differently. המוציא תבן כמלוא פי פרה לגמל, hamotzi teven
kemolei pi para legamal, if it's the straw that would feed a
cow, a mouth... the go in the mouth of a cow and
you're taking out for a camel that needs more, דכולי עלמא לא
פליגי דחייב. dekulei alma lo peligi de-chayav. I got to tell you,
when I heard the debate, both רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish agreed you are חייב. chayav. Okay, the opposite. It's
not there was a consensus you're exempt, there was a consensus you're
חייב chayav because that's a minimum amount to feed a cow, and
the fact that you're interested in a camel does not get you
off the hook. כי פליגי, Ki peligi, when they debated, in the
opposite direction. במוציא אצה, Be-motzi atza, you're taking out this אצה atza
which is again this legume straw that normally is not eaten by
cows and normally has a big size for minimum. כמלוא פי פרה
לפרה, Kemolei pi para le-para, but you are deciding to feed it
to your cow. Okay, so that's sort of like the previous משנה.
Mishnah. Here's this stuff that normally is not fed to cows and
goes by the size of a camel's mouth, big. I say, I
don't have so much straw with me these days, let me actually
feed this to my cow. He won't like it so much but
tough luck. Okay, so I go ahead and I take this out
for my cow and it's the minimum amount for a cow. Does
that change the minimum size? Okay, so that seems a pretty good
question. Can I now be חייב chayav for my subjective reality, more
strict? So let's take a look. דכולי עלמא לא פליגי... dekulei alma
lo peligi... okay, איפכא איתמר, ibra itmar, it was said the reverse.
רבי יוחנן אמר פטור, Rabbi Yochanan amar patur, you're exempt. Go ahead
and I take this out for my cow and it's the minimum
amount for a cow. Does that change the minimum size? Okay, so
that seems a pretty good question. Can I now be חייב chayav
for my subjective reality, more strict? So let's take a look. דכולי
עלמא לא... D'kulei alma lo... איפכא אתמר, iphcha itmar, it was said
the reverse. רבי יוחנן אמר פטור, Rabbi Yochanan amar patur, you're exempt,
because okay, we go by objective, not subjective. ריש לקיש אמר חייב,
Reish Lakish amar chayav, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says you're חייב. chayav.
רבי יוחנן אמר פטור. Rabbi Yochanan amar patur. Now why? How is
this different than the previous משנה Mishna that said if I set
something aside, I can make a smaller size because of my subjective
reality? He says no, here there's something else that kicks in. אכילה
על ידי הדחק לא שמה אכילה, achila al yedei d'chaka lo shma
achila, a type of a forced eating is not considered eating. So
your cow is not going to want to eat this. You might
force your cow to eat this, it might barely get it down,
but that's not really considered to be like that you have actually
fed your cow. So what seems to be the point is like
this: Rabbi Yochanan says I don't disagree that you can create subjective
realities and be חייב chayav for smaller amounts. For example I gave
is you set aside your chewed piece of gum, okay, most people
after it came out of their mouth would throw it out. You're
going to reuse it. Okay, fine, but when you reuse it, you're
actually, the act that you're doing with it is a meaningful act.
Okay, you're chewing your gum, fine, most people think it's disgusting, but
at the end of the day you're chewing your gum. All right,
so, but if when you are setting aside a small amount of
this עמיר amir to feed your cow, that act of feeding the
cow is seen as like a meaningless, not, you know, act. And
therefore, since we don't acknowledge the value of that act, then even
the fact that you set it aside cannot create a lesser amount.
Okay, so therefore here, your subjective reality is not, does not create
it, because what you're doing with it is considered to be completely
illegitimate or completely not recognized and therefore not have meaning. ריש לקיש
אמר חייב, Reish Lakish amar chayav, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says no,
you are חייב, chayav, אכילה על ידי הדחק שמה אכילה. achila al
yedei d'chaka shma achila. That type of an eating is an eating,
so yes, it's not normal, but it's still considered like you, the
animal ate, like you fed it, and therefore there, if you decide
to use it for that purpose, you, we go by your minimum
reality. Yes.
This is for people also, this idea of אכילה
על ידי הדחק?
achila
al yedei d'chaka?
Yes, so that is, it is discussed, and Tosafot actually, first of
all, just discussed other places by animals. Tosafot has a סוגיא sugya
in בבא קמא Bava Kamma about Torts where we actually say אכילה
על ידי הדחק achila al yedei d'chaka is אכילה. achila. So different,
even for animals, different categories. And we have it by issues about,
you know, about יום כיפור Yom Kippur and other types of issues.
So אכילה על ידי הדחק achila al yedei d'chaka is a broad,
broad discussion. Yeah. So did you have an issue? No, Tosafot. Wait
a minute, we're getting to you.
I understand with other מלאכות, melachot, so they have to be constructive
and that is defined as something, you know, that
is not a constructive way. But הוצאה, hotza'ah, it seems like it's
a step removed. You are actually taking this thing, right, from one
domain into another.
Right. So you're saying the very act that you're taking it is,
is subjectively giving it significance. Yeah. Right. So your question is how
do you ever have the case in the משנה Mishna about the
non-subjective significance? I don't understand... Well, Rabbi Yochanan as I said, he
says normally we might go by your subjective significance, but only if
we sort of acknowledge that what you're doing with it is seen
as something other people would see as a meaningful thing to do
with it. Okay, and you are, well if you are... let's say,
I'll give you an example. Let's say, I don't know, let's say
I was going to take out some
some tar because to pour it over my head because I, I
get, I get, I get pleasure out of pouring tar over my
head. Okay, and it's a minimum amount that other, that's not a
minimum amount of tar, right? Would that be considered that I've given
it significance or not? Or we'd say no, even your subjective reality
can give it significance if the thing you're doing with it is
seen as something meaningful. That seems to be Rabbi Yochanan's point. But
I thought what you were asking is: how do you ever get
a case where it's not giving it significance? Since you're taking it
out, you obviously have given it some significance, so you should always
be going by your subjective reality should lower the minimum bar. And
I think that's why the משנה Mishna uses the phrase מצניע. matsnia.
מצניע Matsnia doesn't just mean you are valuing it, but it means
you have actually set it aside. You've already done something to give
it significance. So the fact that you happen to be carrying it,
which demonstrates the fact that you care about it, is not enough.
There has to have been some real sort of setting aside of
it. Yes.
So, and I think it's a very interesting position of אכילה על
ידי הדחק לא שמה אכילה. achila al yedei d'chaka lo shma achila.
So if it's פסח Pesach and I see...
I don't want to talk about that. Okay, moving on. ועד כמלא
פי הטלה. V'ad k'malei pi hatleh. The עמיר amir כמלא פי הטלה,
k'malei pi hatleh, this עמיר amir which we said is some different
type of straw, that fits in the mouth of a sheep. Okay,
which again is therefore the sheep is the smallest animal that will
eat this
עמיר. amir. והתניא כגרוגרת, V'hatanya k'grogeret, but we have another thing that
says actually it goes by the size of a pressed fig. אידי
ואידי חד שיעורא הוא. Idy v'idy chad shiura hu. Okay, they're all
the same. A גרוגרת grogeret is the minimum size of a sheep,
of the, for the sheep. We didn't want to say גרוגרת, grogeret,
Tosafot says, because
to explain where that came from and not that it was maybe
somehow because we were considering it human food. Because גרוגרת grogeret is
always the size we give to human food, so we wanted to
make it clear that that's not the point by this עמיר. amir.
The point by this עמיר amir is is that that is the
amount that fits in the mouth of a sheep. It happens to
be the same as a
גרוגרת. grogeret. Okay. עלי שום ועלי בצלים לחים כגרוגרת. Alei shum v'alei
b'tzalim lachim k'grogeret. So if you have these moist kibel-line? No, okay,
right. But now we're into human food... What actually the way רש"י
Rashi explains it is we're into human food because we're not mentioning
the animals that eat it. So when you have these moist greens
of garlic
or of onions, so I don't know, you know, sometime maybe people
would boil them and use them for something, then it goes, then
it's human food and then it goes by a גרוגרת. grogaret. The
יבשים, yeveishim, dried, then humans don't eat it so the smallest animal
that eats it would be a goat. כמלא פי הגדי, Ke'male pi
hagdi, you go by a goat's mouth. ואין מצטרפין זה עם זה
מפני שלא שוו בשיעוריהן. Ve'ein mitztarfin ze im ze mipne shelo shavu
beshiureihen. And you cannot combine things from different categories of minimum size.
So the גמרא Gemara is now going to look at this idea
of combining from different categories. אמר רב יוסף בר חנינא, Amar Rav
Yosef bar Chanina, רב יוסף בר חנינא Rav Yosef bar Chanina says,
אין מצטרפין לחמור שבהן אבל מצטרפין לקל שבהן. ein mitztarfin lachamur shebahem
aval mitztarfin lakal shebahem. לחמור, Lachamur,
right, so he says you cannot combine to the more stringent category
meaning the smaller size, but you can combine for the more lenient,
the bigger size. What does that mean? It means, so you've got
the cow's mouth food, I'll just call it the cow's mouth and
the camel's mouth food. So you cannot add some camel's mouth food
to give you a full cow's mouth. Why? Because the camel's mouth
food you need more of, so it's not as if you would,
you know, it's not the same amount is of less value, if
you see the point, you need more of it to be חייב.
chayav. So you can't add camel's mouth food to give you the
minimum size for cow's mouth. But you can add cow's mouth food
to give you the minimum size for camel's mouth because cow's mouth
less goes further, right? So therefore the cow's mouth is weightier as
it were and it can be added to the camel's mouth. Now
what's interesting here is all of a sudden we switched from realities
to certain formalisms because nobody is asking the question of but what
if the camel doesn't eat that food? Right? So it might be
nice that you have three quarters of a camel's mouth and one
quarter is made up by the cow's food, but if the camel
doesn't eat it, the whole together isn't usable. Right? And now it
seems like we're not concerned about that. We're just saying a formal
rule: you can combine the categories in this way because you're taking
more strict stuff and using it in a more lenient category. Let's
see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
Just to speak about that once. Yes.
I have taken if you
have three quarters of a mouth of
camel and you add to it one quarter that final one quarter
is made up by cow's food. So you're חייב. chayav. Since cow's
food is you know weightier as it were than camel's food because
less is חייב, chayav, you can use cow's food to make up
the missing quarter of the camel's mouth. Well the גמרא Gemara isn't
discussing whether the camel will eat it. If the camel would eat
it it would seem that it's an obvious point. So it seems
like now we're just going into some formal rule even if maybe
the whole combined isn't meaningful. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אבל מצטרפין לקל שבהן. aval
mitztarfin lakal shebahem. וכל דלא שוו בשיעורי מי מצטרפי? Vechol d'lo shavu
beshiurei mi mitztarfi?
If they don't have the same size, can they really combine? The
same minimum הלכתי halachic size? והתנן? Vehatnan? Didn't we teach in a
משנה: mishnah: הבגד ג' על ג'? Habeged gimal al gimal? If you
have some cloth it has to be three by three טפחים tefachim
to be considered something that if a זב zav sits on it
it's טמא מושב. tamei moshav. Right? The idea of a seat of
a זב zav or of a זבה zava is it becomes an
אב הטומאה av hatumah and it's something that is normally sat on.
So what is the minimum? So if it's made out of cloth,
it's three by three טפחים. tefachim. והשק, Vehasak, if it's made out
of sackcloth, ד' על ד', arba al arba, four by four. והעור,
Veha'or, if it's made out of leather, ה' על ה', chamesh al
chamesh, five by five. מפץ, Mapatz, if it's a mat, ו' על
ו', shesh al shesh, six by six טפחים. tefachim. Okay, those are
minimum sizes. Okay, let's say you are going to make some type
of a seat which is a little bit of each of these.
Can they combine across categories? Okay, ותניא עלה, vetanya ala, we taught
on this: הבגד והשק והשק והעור והעור והמפץ מצטרפין זה עם זה
habeged vehasak vehasak veha'or veha'or vehamapatz mitztarfin ze im ze that you
can combine across categories presumably if you are combining like we said
using the more strict category for the more lenient. Okay also it's
interesting, one of the תוספות Tosafot thinks that you can't combine you
can only combine with the category most near you. You can't jump
leapfrog over a category, right? בגד beged can combine with שק sak
and שק sak can combine with עור or but בגד beged and
עור or maybe not. Anyway that's very confusing why it should be
limited that way. But anyway we seem to have our rule: you
can combine across categories presumably if you use a stricter category to
fill up the amount of a more lenient category. But now the
גמרא Gemara says: but that's because of something special. Why is that
true there? ואמר רבי שמעון מה טעם, Ve'amar Rabbi Shimon mah ta'am,
why is it that you can combine across categories? מפני שראויים לטמא
מושב. Mipne she're'uyim letamei moshav. Because
they are fit to become to make a מושב. moshav. Now what
does that mean? That sounds like very circular reasoning. We're trying to
say is this a minimum amount for the category of מושב moshav
of a seat of a זב zav and you say yes they
can combine across categories because they can combine to make a מושב.
moshav. So it sounds very tautological or very circular. So what תוספות
Tosafot says here and רש"י Rashi says in סוכה Sukkah is what
it means is: no. What it means is although they have different
minimum amounts that's just in a case where they haven't been specifically
designated. But if you actually cut out a swath one by one
טפח tefach and for the purpose of using it as some type
of a seat, then that is a שיעור shiur that applies across
all categories. So therefore, on the one hand, they're in different categories,
but there's one way in which they all have the same category,
the same minimum size. If you specifically cut out a swath of
one by one, they all go by that. So again, this is
a formal rule. Since in one way they share a minimum size,
that allows you to combine them across categories, even when you haven't
specifically cut it out for that purpose. Okay, so the point is,
that's a special case. So therefore, טעמא דראוי לטמי מושב, ta'ama dera'uy
letamei moshav, the reason you're allowed to combine across categories is because
there's this way in which they all have the same minimum size.
אבל אינו ראוי לטמי מושב, aval eino ra'uy letamei moshav, if you
never have a case where they all have the same minimum size,
לא, lo, you couldn't combine across categories. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says
רבא, Rava, הכא נמי חזי לדוגמא, hacha nami chazi ledigma,
here too, there is a way that they all have the same
size. What's the way they all have the same size? If you
are not interested in it to feed your animal, you're interested in
it as a sample, right? You know, so the, so you know
you have like the paint samples and you have a lot of
things, you know, where a sample cloth. So if you're not, so
therefore if you're, when you're interested in it to use it as
a sample, then they all have the same minimum amount, which is
even כל שהוא, kol shehu, even a tiniest amount serves as a
sample. So what we're saying is again, this has become a very
formal rule now. Since all these different foods, if you were in
the business of selling cow food, selling camel food, right, and you
were using this as a sample, it would be even the smallest
amount. So since all of these different foods in that scenario being
used as a sample have the same minimum amount, which is nothing,
which is the tiniest amount, therefore even now that they're being used
to feed the animals, there's enough that puts them in somewhat of
the same category that you can combine the cow's food for the
camel's food. Okay, but notice this seems like very formal rules of
how we're allowed to combine things across categories because in some other
case they're in the same category and it's strict and you can
use the strict stuff for the leniency stuff and what we're not
asking is, okay, but this whole mix that I have right now
serves no purpose, right? My camel won't eat it and my cow
won't eat it. So and that seems in this case not to
matter. Once we have defined, and that's really important to realize and
this happens a lot in הלכה, halacha, that there are certain things
that are like historical. There are some things which are the background
of how we got to this type of definition or legislation if
it's a דרבנן. derabbanan. But once we got to that definition and
legislation, then we go by the rules, then it becomes a formal
category. So it could have been what defined these minimum sizes were
camel and cow and sheep and goat and all these things. But
at the end of the day, now we don't look at them
as camel and cow and sheep and goat, we look, this is
X size, this is Y size, this is Z size, can you
combine the different sizes and it becomes much more of a formal
question than of what was behind these categories to begin with. Yeah.
Can things change? Like let's say, you know, my cereal which on
שבת Shabbat has a minimum size, but then on פסח Pesach I
can't use it at all? I understand.
Well, I'm not going to get... איסור הנאה issur hana'ah might be
different, but I tell you, you're asking a different question which is,
if it's איסור הנאה issur hana'ah then yes, that makes things different,
but that's not just time. I think you're asking like, do these
sizes change based on different societal norms? Okay, and that is an
interesting question and it goes to what I'm saying, how much does
the history of how we got these minimum sizes, you know, is
that an active concern or how much once they've been crystallized as
this is the minimum, then that becomes the objective? Now here at
least we know that subjective realities can make it a smaller size,
right? That's again a bizarre thing that we have by carrying we
don't have elsewhere, that your subjective reality or whatever, it's very uncommon,
that your subjective reality can actually make it a smaller size. But
maybe, you know, if all of society uses things differently, could that
actually maybe change it to a larger size? And that ties into
exactly what I'm saying. How much are we now left with formal
categories as opposed to how much is the original reason still active?
Let's take a look now as we finish up this פרק. perek.
המוציא אוכלין כגרגרת חייב ומצטרפין זה עם זה. Hamotzi ochalin kegargeret chayav
umitzstarfin zeh im zeh. Food, meaning human food, you're חייב chayav and
it's a type of thing obviously that people care about and B,
you can combine different types of food and the minimum size is
a גרוגרת, grogaret, a pressed fig, and you can combine different types
of food. Again, why? Because formally they have the same size even
though you would never eat it together. So if you take out,
you know, right, you take out like some peanut butter and some,
I don't know, a little bit of peanut butter and a little
bit of strawberries and a little bit of who knows what, hot
sauce or something like that, you know, all of that combined to
a גרוגרת grogaret even though you have nothing to use this for.
Okay, so that again becomes this more formal rule. ומצטרפין זה עם
זה מפני ששוו בשיעוריהם umitzstarfin zeh im zeh mipnei sheshavu bishiureihem because
they do have the same size. Now, חוץ מקליפתן והגרעינין ואקציהם, chutz
miklipatan vehagarinin ve'uktzeihen, here is the following things that really don't, aren't
considered
food: shells, and seeds of food because these are things that are
not normally
eaten, and the twigs, you know, like the... What but what do
you call that thing on the top of stem, the stem וסובין
ומורסן v'subin u'mursan and two different types of like bran about itself?
No, or even in combination, these are things that are not considered
food and therefore do not combine. I know. So the גמרא's Gemara
going to ask about bran. Okay. Rabbi Yehuda says, רבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda omer, Rabbi Yehuda says חוץ מקליפי עדשים שמתבשלות עמהם. chutz
miklipei adashim she'mitbashlot imahem. There's one exception to this rule, which is
the shells of certain types of legumes which are which you would
cook them with and eat, right? We know sometimes people eat like
green peas but aren't there some type of like lentils? Lentils, okay,
so right. And do people eat shells and also peels? No, I
do not believe so. No, we're not talking about like apple peels.
Right. We're talking about like orange peels.
Orange peels, yes, meaning I think קליפה klipa pretty much I think
is like the sort of hard non-edible external thing, right? Like banana,
right, but right, right, right, right, right, not skins, but yes, it
would presume it would include peels like banana peels, right, banana peels,
orange peels and so on. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says וסובין
ומורסן לא מצטרפי? v'subin u'mursan lo mitztarfei? Is it true that these
different types of bran don't combine? והתנן v'ha'tnan we taught in the
משנה Mishna חמשת רבעים קמח ועוד חייבין בחלה. chameshet reva'im kemach v'od
chayavin b'challa. That how much is a minimum amount of flour to
be חייב chayav in חלה? challa? Five, you know, רבעים reva'im and
a little. So whatever, I'm not going to get into exactly what
that amount is, but the more important that's the minimum size. And
the more important part for us is הן וסובן ומורסן hen v'suban
u'morsan even if the flour is made up of the fine flour,
the fine bran, and the coarse bran. All of that creates a
minimum amount to be חייב chayav in חלה. challa. Now obviously there's
a little difference there because there you actually are making it into
dough. You're adding water to it and you actually are making it
into dough. But anyway אמר אביי amar Abaye שכן עני אוכל פיתו
בעיסה בלוסה. sheken ani ochel pito b'isa belusa. He says yes, you're
right, a poor person will eat his bread with a dough made
probably means made out of a dough that has bran in it,
but that's not significant enough to define it as a normal minimum.
Now of course if you are planning on eating bran, right, or
then you are the עני ani that goes back to the point
that you can make a small if your subjective reality can make
a smaller size, but if you weren't even aware what was in
your bag or you're not an עני ani or whatever, then this
is not considered to be of objective value. So again that's interesting
because a clear segment of society, the poor, which is presumably a
non-trivial segment, that actually values this and that's not enough to define
it as a of a minimum size that we go by a
wider swath of society and again raises the question about what is
that sort of how do we determine who are those people we're
looking at. I understand. רבי יהודה אומר חוץ מקליפי עדשים המתבשלות עמהם.
Rabbi Yehuda omer chutz miklipei adashim hamitbashlot imahem. The one thing we
exclude is the shells of עדשים. adashim. עדשים adashim are lentils, right?
I don't even know what a lentil is. Okay, that are cooked
with them. So גמרא Gemara says עדשים אין פולין לא? adashim in
pulin lo? Lentils yes, but beans no? פולין, pulin, whatever, how does
it legumes beans, all right. Anyway, I really don't know these things.
I mean, you know, these various vegetables or whatnot anyway והתניא v'ha'tanya
רבי יהודה אומר חוץ מקליפי פולין ועדשים. Rabbi Yehuda omer chutz miklipei
pulin v'adashim. Rabbi Yehuda says he excludes both the the the shells
of lentils and of beans or beans and of lentils. So the
גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא. lo kashya. It's not difficult. הא בחדתי
הא בעתיקי. ha b'chadti ha b'atiki. When do we say that the
shells of beans are something that people cook? When they're fresh. But
when they're old they don't. עתיקי מאי טעמא לא? atiki mai ta'ama
lo? Old why do they not cook it and throw it out?
Yeah, אמר רבי אבהו. amar Rabbi Abbahu. But the גמרא Gemara actually
has a more interesting reason מפני שנראין כזבובים בקערה. mipnei she'nir'in k'zvuvim
b'ke'ara. Okay, they're little bit they become little dark specks and it
looks like you've got flies in your dish. So even though maybe
they are edible nobody wants them after they start turning. Right, so
that's like my son if there's a little bruise on the apple
he won't eat it even though it tastes fine but for him
no no longer usable. Okay הדרן עלך כלל גדול. hadran alach klal
gadol. That is the end of כלל גדול klal gadol which as
I said has now shifted us once again into talking about carrying.
So minimum size is relevant for everything but again this hyper focus
on issues about carrying and what's the minimum size and now we
look at the beginning of the next פרק. perek. המוציא יין. hamotzi
yayin. Now we talked food is a גרוגרת. grogeret. How about drink?
So drink goes by different שיעורים. shiurim. Very interesting. So wine כדי
מזיגת הכוס. k'dei mzigat hakos. The amount that you would use to
mix a cup. What they would have they had very very dense
and like you know potent wine and they would actually drink it
after mixing it with water either a two to one ratio or
a three to one ratio. So if you have this dense wine
this unmixed wine it's the minimum amount that you would use to
do a mixing and to create a full cup of wine, right?
So that's more or less a mouthful. What we we'll see what
it is. חלב chalav milk כדי גמיעה. k'dei gmi'a. The minimum amount
for swallowing. Now there's a very interesting תוספות Tosfot who discusses another
place where milk goes by a different שיעור shiur by a גרוגרת
grogeret I think and he gets into the whole question of let
me. He says, yeah, גרוגרת. grogeret. And he gets into the very
interesting discussion about what is סתם stam milk used for? Right? We,
milk of course is a regular thing we drink, but that's a
relatively recent thing that milk is drunk as a drink as widespread
as we do it right now. And the primarily they would use
it for making cheese. So when you look at milk, do you
look at it as a type of cheese pre-made cheese, or do
you look at it as a drink? So here we say גמיעה,
gmiah, we're treating it as a drink and the amount of a
swallow. Okay, in another גמרא Gemara when it talks about how much
milk of milking a cow do you have to do, it says
the amount that would make a גרוגרת grogeret would have a press
date and that's seeing it as a part of a pre-cheese. And
תוספות Tosfot discusses which is the סתם, stam, which is the norm
that we assume is the case by milk. דבש, Devash, now if
it's honey, כדי ליתן על הכתית, kedei litein al hakatit, it's the
minimum amount of honey that you would put on a wound, and
רש"י Rashi says either an animal wound or some people say it's
a person's wound, but they would put some honey on it as
a type of a treatment. שמן, Shemen, oil, כדי לסוך אבר קטן,
kedei lasuch eiver katan, the amount to anoint one, you know, rub
into even a small limb like a pinky. מים, Mayim, water, כדי
לשוף בהן את הכילור kedei lashuf bahen et hakilor is in order
to sort of use it to put onto some type of a
poultice, onto some type of a, you know, again, some type of
a thing that's put on a wound and you add some water
in it, so that's the minimum amount. So what's the smallest kind
of wound? Yeah, that's a good question. I don't know. So what's
interesting about these things is that what, what? רש"י Rashi says an
eye patch. Oh, כילור kilor specifically an eye patch? Okay. All right,
so but interesting about all of these is that that most of
them is because you would use them as non-drink you wouldn't use
them as not drinks, you would use them for other purposes. But
it is worth noting that even when you're using it as a
drink, there's a difference. Wine one way, milk another way. So it's
not just when you use them for non-drink purposes, there could be
different types of drinks and it goes by different amounts. ושאר כל
המשקין ברביעית, u'shear kol hamashkin birvi'it, all other drinks that other than
we've mentioned go by רביעית, revi'it, a quarter of a לוג, log,
which is about three and a half ounces. Okay, so wine and
milk are the exception. Normal things that are drunk and not used
in these other ways is a רביעית. revi'it. וכל השופכין ברביעית, ve'chol
hashofchin birvi'it, also all sort of dirty water, you know, stinky water,
is a רביעית. revi'it. So what do you need that for? So
we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. רבי שמעון אומר כולן ברביעית, Rabbi
Shimon omer kulan birvi'it, all of these things are רביעית, revi'it, okay,
even wine, even honey, even milk, everything. ולא נאמרו כל השיעורין הללו
אלא למצניעיהן, ve'lo neemru kol hashiurin halalu ela lematzni'eihen, and and it
seems like is this an additional thing or explaining it seems like
it's an additional thing, all of these minimum sizes number one, all
the the minimum is a רביעית, revi'it, not what you said all
these subdivisions by liquids. Number two, all these minimums are only for
people that this is a significant amount. But maybe for or that
specifically put it aside. But for other people that maybe it's not
a significant
amount, maybe the minimum would be less would be bigger
and it would be more lenient. Okay, and that's the position we
said before that the earlier משנה Mishnah has rejected. גמרא Gemara on
יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Okay. Yes. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. תנא, Tana, כדי מזיגת כוס יפה, kedei mzigas kos yafeh,
the amount to make a nice cup of wine, which means a
full cup which basically means a רביעית. revi'it. So the amount of
this potent wine that you would mix it and get a רביעית.
revi'it. ומאי כוס יפה, u'mai kos yafeh, what's a nice cup of
wine? כוס של ברכה, kos shel beracha, the amount you'd make a
ברכה beracha on, which again is a רביעית. revi'it. אמר רב נחמן
אמר רבה בר אבוה, amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Abbuha, כוס
של ברכה צריך שיהיה בו רובע רביעית, kos shel beracha tzarich sheyehei
bo rova revi'it, you have to put the dense wine of a
quarter of a רביעית revi'it in the cup of ברכה, beracha, כדי
שימזגנו ויעמיד על רביעית, kedei sheyimzagnu veye'amid al revi'it, because then you'll
add water to it and then the full then it will become
a רביעית. revi'it. So what would be the ratio of water to
wine that you're mixing? If a quarter of a רביעית revi'it plus
water makes a רביעית? revi'it? Not hard math here. A what? Or
an eighth and an eighth to get a quarter? You have a
quarter of this wine of of a רביעית, revi'it, you add water
and the combination is now a full רביעית. revi'it. So you had
three quarters of a water, so it's a three-to-one ratio. אמר רבא
אף אנן נמי תנינא, amar Rava af anan nami tanyana, we taught
similarly, המוציא יין כדי מזיגת כוס, hamotzi yayin kedei mzigas kos, that
wine that we would use to mix a cup of wine. ותני
עלה ve'tanyala כדי מזיגת כוס יפה. kedei mzigas kos yafeh. And we
said of mixing a nice cup. Okay, so how does that prove
a quarter of a רביעית? revi'it? דתניא סיפא de'tania seifa ושאר כל
המשקין ברביעית, u'shear kol hamashkin birvi'it, combine all the points. The basic
other all liquids are רביעית. revi'it. So what's a liquid? Another liquid
is not your dense wine but your mixed wine. So if you're
taking out your mixed wine, what's the minimum amount? A רביעית, revi'it,
right? It's only your dense wine that is that is to mix
how much you need to mix. So if your mixed wine is
a רביעית, revi'it, and then you have your dense wine and the
dense wine is enough to make a significant amount that would fill
a cup, so it's the amount that would make turn into a
רביעית. revi'it. Okay, now, but that's only assuming a three-to-one ratio, right?
ורבא לטעמיה, ve'Rava letamei, Rava goes according to... his reasoning דאמר רבא
d'amar Rava כל חמרא דלא דרי על תלת מיא kol chamra d'lo
dari al tlas maya any wine that you do not mix with
a three kinds as much water לאו חמרא הוא lav chamra hu
is not real wine. Okay, so you understand how the גמרא Gemara
is getting it. Our משנה Mishna is big. Our משנה Mishna says
this dense wine, I'll call it this dense wine, a minimum amount
to make, in order to make a cup. Okay. What's a cup?
So the גמרא Gemara says, a significant cup. How much is that?
Well, we know that all other liquids, including mixed wine, the minimum
amount of significance is a רביעית. revi'is. So it's the amount of
wine that you would need, dense wine you would need to make
a רביעית revi'is of mixed wine. And since רבא Rava says it's
a three to one ratio, therefore it is a quarter of a
רביעית. revi'is. Okay. All this previous גמרא Gemara in the last at
the end of the last פרק. perek. In that, about combining, it's
kind of a little bit thematic. You mean because of combining water?
That you're giving it significance? Right. Although here you're giving it significance
without taking out the water, just its potential. And that's essentially we're
going to read a little bit more, just to finish this thought.
And that's essentially what אביי Abaye answers. אמר אביי שתי תשובות בדבר.
amar Abaye shtei teshuvos badavar. I have two responses to that. חדא
דתנן chada d'tnan ומזוג שני חלקי מים ואחד יין מן היין השרוני.
u'mazug shenei chelkei mayim v'echad yayin min hayayin Hasharoni. So we're bringing
in נדה Niddah twice today. When it talks about reds that
are of blood of
נדה Niddah that is a problematic red, it says
if it looks like mixed wine. And what's mixed wine? It's
a two to one ratio from this wine from the שרון Sharon
valley. Okay. So you see it assumes that wine is a two
to one ratio of water, mixed with two times as much water,
not three to one. Number one. Right. Maybe it's just שרוני. Sharoni.
So let's see what רבא Rava anyway. ועוד, v'od, that's point number
one. It's a two to one ratio, not a three to one.
מים בכד מצטרפין? mayim bekad mitztarfin? The water is still in the
pitcher and you're combining it to this wine. So if this wine
by itself can't be used, you need to add water, how does
that turn it into a minimum amount of significance? סו אמר ליה
רבא, so amar leih Rava, so רבא Rava said הא דקאמרת ha
d'ka'amart שני חלקי מים ואחד יין מן היין השרוני. shenei chelkei mayim
v'echad yayin min hayayin Hasharoni. You said it, that tells you a
two to one ratio of wine from this שרון Sharon wine for
checking bloodstains. יין השרוני לחוד דריפי. yayin Hasharoni lachud d'rifi. First of
all, it's שרון Sharon wine. That's different. That is weaker. It's not
as potent, and therefore you can't put in as much water. אי
נמי ei nami or else say התם משום חזותא. hasam mishum chazusa.
There, we're saying specifically how to determine a color to use to
check for bloodstains. Okay. That doesn't mean that's the normal way in
which it's made if you want to drink it. אבל לטעמא aval
l'ta'ama if you want to drink it and taste it בעא טפי
ba'ei tfei then you need more water, three to one. So that's
not a proof. That's talking about different things, different types of wine,
different types of purpose. The normal ratio is three to one. ודקאמרת
u'd'ka'amart and what you said מים בכד, mayim bekad, it should be
probably בכד, bekad, ומצטרפין, u'mitztarfin, how do you think the water is
still in the pitcher and you're combining it? So what? לעניין שבת
מידי דחשיב בעינן והא נמי חשיב. l'inyan Shabbos midi d'chashiv ba'inan v'ha
nami chashiv. By שבת Shabbos it's going by what is significant. And
since this amount of wine is going to be the ingredients that
you're going to use, if like I took out, you know, we
have these little packets of crystal light in the hull, right, that
have like one, you use for making one pitcher of crystal light.
Sometimes you have even smaller, making one cup. Anyway, so if I
take out one of those packets, that's significant because yes, I can't
do anything with it right now, but that is like a significant
size of this thing for the use I want to put it
to. The funny thing is that אביי Abaye has to agree that
you don't have to combine the water because the משנה Mishna says,
a minimum amount that is needed to make a cup of wine.
But it seems that אביי Abaye was reacting that a quarter of
a רביעית revi'is is too small of significance. So he thinks it's
a two to one ratio. He might say a third of a
רביעית. revi'is. But a quarter of a רביעית revi'is he rejects, and
how can you use the water to give it significance? And רבא
Rava says, yeah, because that is the amount that is going to
be used once mixed with water, it will actually be significant. So
therefore this has significance in itself because of how you're going to
use it. So we will continue here tomorrow. Where's the... you recently
mentioned that the... wine was more potent, that's not true. Yeah, I
was wondering about that. Like how of a sudden does wine become
more potent? Customary, the use of places to add more water. It's
so funny, because it would seem that if you try to add
water to our wine, it would really seem very bland and tasteless
and so on. But maybe the point is they didn't have soda.
So it was a nice way of having flavored stuff without being
as alcoholic, you know. I don't know, but I thought that as
well. Like how grapes are grapes. Oh yeah? That's interesting, I don't
know enough about that. Is very dense, it's either... bit thicker. Alright,
chance take.